So, what's this? Rubens is the nastiest,
most vulgar painter that ever lived.
His pictures always put me in mind of
chamber pots.
Ha!
Thomas Eakins. [music]
So, what's this?
Hm.
To my eye, Rubens' coloring [music] is
contemptible. His shadows are filthy
brown, somewhat the color of excrement.
William Blake.
What's this?
He's gifted, [music]
but he's used his gifts to make nasty
things.
Picasso.
>> [music]
[bell]
>> The modern world really has it in for
Rubens. It's as if everything he did
jars with our sensibilities and goes
against our grain.
His religious pictures are completely
over the top, aren't they?
Too violent, too noisy, too Catholic.
His mythologies are even worse.
All those fleshy pink gods doing silly
things in ridiculous mythological
pantomimes.
>> [laughter]
>> And as for his women, oh my god, Rubens'
women.
They're just too fat, aren't they?
Women in art shouldn't carry this much
cellulite.
So, that's what people think, but it's
not what I think. I think Rubens was one
of the most exciting painters the world
has seen. Just look at all that
invention,
that energy,
that drama.
So, yes, I'm a Rubens man.
And in this film, I'm going to try and
make all of you
Rubens people, too.
>> [music]
>> I was never so disgusted in my life as
with Rubens and his eternal wives.
Lord Byron. Eternal wives. Ah.
When Lord Byron complains about Rubens'
eternal wives,
he's complaining about all those
notoriously large women
in Rubens' art.
The modern world simply doesn't tolerate
women like this,
does it?
But why not? Seriously, why not?
What's wrong with a few bulges and a bit
of cellulite?
Don't tell me nobody out there's got
any.
Even I've got a bit of cellulite.
Besides, if you look back at the art of
the past,
the best evidence there is of the human
worldview,
if you go right back to the beginning,
you'll see that Rubens' women
are the norm, not the exception.
This is the Willendorf Venus, the oldest
known masterpiece of sculpture.
Her task is to ensure human fertility.
She's a bringer of life, a good luck
charm.
And look how fleshy and Rubenzian she
is.
And in any case, not all Rubens' women
were like that. They weren't all fleshy
housewives.
Some of them
were women of remarkable power and
confidence.
I mean,
see all this?
Everything in this room,
this entire Rubenzian outpouring, all of
it,
is about one woman.
That woman
over there.
The art-loving queen of France,
Marie de Medici.
>> [music]
>> There she is being born. As a Medici,
she was born in Florence, and that's why
there are all these cherubs down here
popping out of the River Arno to welcome
her.
Here she is at school being educated by
the gods.
Apollo is teaching her music.
Hermes teaches languages.
Over here, that's the French King Henry
the fourth seeing her picture and liking
it.
Henry liked it so much he married her.
But don't worry. I'm not going to take
you through all of it. There's still
most of the room to go.
21 pictures in all taking up a huge slab
of the Louvre. [music]
But we're here for Rubens, not for Marie
de Medici.
And there's a big Rubensian truth I want
to tackle in here about the impact of
his work.
You know when you first come in here and
you see all this, you're tempted to walk
a bit faster, aren't you? To give most
of this a miss. Don't worry, we all feel
like that. I mean, all this
is terrifying, right?
With Rubens, there's so much to look at,
isn't there?
Too much.
His art sometimes forms an impenetrable
blob of bodies that frighten you away.
Here's a good example. Rubens is full of
the damned.
It's just scary, isn't it?
Have you ever seen so many bodies in one
picture?
But then, when you step closer and start
giving it a good look,
see what happens.
The fleshy blobs start to disentangle
themselves and make sense.
The details emerge.
And they're fascinating.
Look at that. Ooh.
And that.
Ooh.
Ah.
The point is, Rubens always gave more
than was asked of him.
He was so inventive and daring, had so
much fun painting his pictures.
From a distance, that's not always
obvious. From a distance, Rubens can
seem frightening.
But if you get closer to him,
close enough to see what he's actually
up to,
Rubens
is absolutely delightful.
And guess what?
You have an ally in this exciting
exploration.
The camera.
The camera loves Rubens.
It gets you close enough to see his
details,
high enough to inspect his corners.
Since this painting left Rubens' studio,
no one's been able to see it as well as
[music] this.
So, yes, stick with me.
Stick with the camera.
And let's plunge together
into all that Rubens out there.
Before we go an inch further into this
film,
we need to have a geography lesson.
This is
>> [laughter]
>> a famous map called the Leo Belgicus,
and it was brought out in 1609 by a
cartographer called Klaus Janszoon
Visscher, and it shows Western Europe as
it was in Rubens's time.
The lion shows the outline of what used
to be called the Spanish Netherlands.
Today, it's three different countries.
Belgium, around here,
Holland, up here,
and over here, Luxembourg.
It was called the Spanish Netherlands
because all these lands belonged then to
the Spanish kings who'd inherited them
from the Burgundians, and it was divided
up into provinces, 17 of them.
These 17 provinces were split on
religious lines.
Up here were the Protestants, the
Calvinists.
Down here, in the Flemish bit, were the
Catholics.
So, this part and this part were at
loggerheads. Then, in 1568,
the simmering tension between the
Calvinist north and the Catholic south
erupted into a terrible war, one of the
most brutal and longest wars in European
history, called the Eighty Years' War.
Now, Rubens was born in 1577,
just after the fighting started.
He died in 1640,
a few years before it finished.
So, for his entire life, all 63 years of
it,
the north was fighting the south.
The Catholics were fighting the
Protestants.
It's the only reality he ever knew.
>> All that was happening around him all
the time. And it's against that backdrop
that his life and his art was enacted.
>> The conflict in the Netherlands stamped
on everything.
Not just history and maps,
but entire families, too.
>> Rubens' father, Jan Rubens, was a lawyer
from Antwerp and, interestingly, a
Protestant, a Calvinist. And when the 80
Years War broke out in 1568,
this Jan Rubens had to flee from Antwerp
to escape an invading Spanish army that
had turned up to enforce Catholicism and
kill the Protestants.
>> He fled here, to Germany,
where there was plenty of work going for
a Protestant lawyer.
>> Unfortunately, that's how he came into
contact with this woman here, Anna of
Saxony, the local princess, who employed
him to sort out some financial matters.
>> Now, this Anna of Saxony was fascinating
but flawed.
Very flawed.
She liked to drink and she liked men.
And as her new lover,
she chose Jan Rubens.
>> Jan was also married. He had brought his
wife with him from Antwerp.
But when a princess seduces you,
all the rules get broken, don't they?
>> Their affair was short and grubby.
Anna got pregnant
and Jan Rubens was quickly imprisoned
for the very, very serious crime of
adultery with a princess.
He was in jail for 2 years.
And when they finally let him out,
he moved back in with the wife he'd
betrayed
and proceeded to have more children with
her.
Including in 1577,
the year Anna of Saxony died,
a son
called Peter Paul Rubens.
>> Now, Rubens' mother, Marie Pypelinckx,
seems to have been a rather reluctant
Calvinist. And when Jan Rubens also died
in 1587,
she took the family back to Antwerp,
where they returned to a fully Catholic
life as if nothing had happened.
>> Rubens was 10 when he arrived in
Antwerp.
He was put in a Catholic school
and then trained as a painter.
His talent was obvious.
And the new rulers of the Spanish
Netherlands,
the Habsburg Archdukes Albert and
Isabella,
were quick to notice him and make him a
favorite.
But when you look at this early Adam and
Eve,
painted soon after he finished his
apprenticeship,
it's worth remembering
that the sin of lust was embedded in his
childhood.
That religion and its conflicts had
stamped on his history.
And that his betrayed mother
was the only religious constant he
really knew.
Why did Rubens paint so many Madonnas
and children?
And why are they all so soppy?
I think it's because they're personal.
Very personal.
The Rubens family house was up here in
Sint-Michielsstraat.
Just around the corner, meanwhile,
in Kloosterstraat,
lived the family of Jan Brant, an
Antwerp lawyer who had a vivacious
daughter called Isabella. Isabella
Brant.
Isabella was charming, sparky,
fun to be with,
and hard working.
She liked to roll up her sleeves and get
things done,
which is what Rubens liked to do too.
She lived so close to him they could
hardly fail to meet and soon enough they
were courting and not long after in 1609
they got married.
Rubens was 32 when he married Isabella.
She was 18.
But that was normal at the time.
They moved into this big house here, the
Rubens house.
And as he was to do with all the people
in his life
Rubens began putting Isabella into his
art.
Sometimes he did it officially as in
their touching wedding picture in the
outer pinakothek in Munich.
Rubens and Isabella sitting in a
honeysuckle bower.
All loved up and content.
>> [music]
>> Other times Isabella is likely
disguised.
Here she is pretending to be the Virgin
Mary looking after the baby Jesus.
And I'm pretty sure Jesus is actually
their first son, Albert.
Born in 1614.
And if I'm not wrong and I don't think I
am
isn't this her as well? Gone blonde for
a moment.
And popping up so cheekily as a jolly
follower of Bacchus in one of Rubens'
fleshiest mythologies.
The drunken Silenius. [music]
They were married for 18 years until her
early death in 1626.
And in that time God only knows how many
Isabella Brandts popped up
surreptitiously
in her husband's art.
In front of Rubens, put on blinkers like
those a horse wears.
Jean-Auguste-Dominique
Ingres
Ingres that
horse blinkers. Ah!
You don't need blinkers to look at
Rubens.
What you need
is a bigger telly.
Is there anyone called Chris watching
this film? Like Chris Froome, the
cyclist, or Chris Martin, the pop
singer.
Well, if you are watching, all you
Chrises out there, this bit of the film
is dedicated to you.
Chrises of the world,
how often do you consider the true
significance of your name?
What does Christopher really mean?
And what's it got to do with this
stupendous Rubens masterpiece,
the Descent from the Cross in Antwerp
Cathedral?
You have to follow me round here.
See that huge fellow up there on the
back of the side wings?
That is St. Christopher.
And he's carrying Christ across the
river.
Because Christopher, of course, means
carrier of Christ.
Now, St. Christopher was the patron
saint of an organization called the
Arquebusiers Guild.
The Arquebusiers used these things.
Arquebuses.
A big new gun that revolutionized
warfare in the Eighty Years' War.
Here in the Spanish Netherlands, with
their endless wars, the arquebus was
constantly in use. And in Antwerp, the
Arquebusiers had formed their own
militia, a kind of territorial army,
whose task was to defend the city.
And the president of this Arquebusiers
Guild was a man called Nicolaas Rockox.
That's him on the left, standing behind
the old man.
In 1611,
Rockox and the Arquebusiers
commissioned Rubens to paint a new
altarpiece for Antwerp Cathedral.
It's his most famous painting
and probably
his greatest.
But to get back to all you Christophers
out there,
this idea of carrying Christ
is what unites all the bits of this
dramatic and magnificent altarpiece.
So, in the middle, the dead body of
Christ is being carried from the cross.
He suffered his terrible crucifixion,
and now it's time to bury him.
You can really feel the weight of his
corpse, can't you? There's all these
helpers and apostles lower him down from
the cross, but it's these women at the
foot of the cross towards whom it all
seems to be slumping.
On the left, at the bottom,
Mary of Cleophas, so youthfully
beautiful, sheds a desperate tear.
Next to her, Mary Magdalene, the
reformed prostitute, lets Jesus' foot
rest on her shoulder
and makes him suddenly appear
weightless.
So, everyone here is carrying Christ,
and that's what this central panel is
about. But over here, on the left,
Rubens winds back the clock to the time
before Jesus is born, to the so-called
Visitation.
And there's the Blessed Mary again, the
rather unlikely blonde with the red top.
And as you can see, she's heavily
pregnant.
She's come [music] to visit her cousin,
Elizabeth.
And she's carrying Jesus in her womb.
These days, the picture's always open,
but in Rubens' time, it was often
closed.
Like that.
With St. Christopher over here and the
old hermit on the other side. And then,
when they opened it,
all this was revealed.
It's like 17th century cinema, isn't it?
Dramatic,
emotional,
vivid.
And all you Christophers out there,
I want to thank you
for this.
Nicolaas Rockox, the president of the
Arquebusiers, who commissioned Rubens'
Great Descent from the Cross,
lived in this house here.
Rockox was the mayor of Antwerp several
times, a very powerful and influential
man. A good man for Rubens to have on
his side. And that's him there upon the
left of this devotional triptych that
Rubens painted for him.
And his wife,
she's on the other side.
Lucky old Rockox had Rubens' all round
the house.
But
the one I want to focus on now
used to hang here above the fireplace
where that Rubens' Venus is now.
And in Rockox's time, this position here
was occupied by a very naughty picture.
A picture which calls for some music.
>> [music]
>> The story of Samson and Delilah is told
in the book of Judges.
She was a woman from the Valley of
Sorek.
He was an Israelite famed for his great
strength.
The Philistines, traditional enemies of
the Israelites, promised Delilah money.
1,100 pieces of silver
to find out the secret of Samson's
strength.
At first, he resisted her.
But after a night of intense biblical
[music] lovemaking,
Samson could resist no more.
>> [music]
[music]
>> So, Delilah finds out that the secret of
Samson's strength is his long hair. And
in the Rubens painting, the Philistines
have just arrived at the door.
And they've brought a barber with them.
It's such an exciting picture.
Rubens doesn't just bring the Bible to
life.
He sets it on fire.
And will you look at Samson, exhausted
by all that sweaty sex,
just lying there, relaxed,
like a goalkeeper who's banged his head
against the post.
>> [music]
>> So, Nicholas Rockox commissions Rubens
to paint a big warning about the
seductive power of women, and to put it
above the mantelpiece here, where no one
can miss it.
And what does Rubens do?
Well, Rubens paints him one of the
sexiest pictures in the whole of Baroque
An utterly tangible depiction of
postcoital exhaustion.
And if you look around Rubens's art of
these busy years,
you'll find lots of Delilahs scattered
about his crowd scenes tempting the
Samsons.
All these beautiful blondes don't just
look like Delilah.
They are Delilah.
The same blonde model popping in and out
of Rubens's art
like a Baroque Barbara Windsor in a
Carry On.
>> [music]
>> Sometimes, as in this particularly
violent depiction of the Massacre of the
Innocents,
she's even wearing the same dress.
Other times,
she's not.
>> [music]
>> So, how does Rubens do it?
How does he make his art so vivid?
To find out, I've wangled my way into a
top secret Antwerp warehouse.
>> Hello. Hello.
>> Where a team of busy restorers is
working on a Rubens Madonna.
>> Thank you for letting me in here.
>> It's painted, as most of his best work
was painted,
not on canvas,
but on wood.
>> Uh Antwerp, in fact, uh the Antwerp
school of painting is one of the few
schools that is still painting on wood
in the early uh 17th century.
Uh the tradition of painting on wood in
in Flanders had a long tradition, of
course, since the times of Van Eyck and
and Bruegel.
And uh
on on the uh the smooth panels
every every brushstroke is visible
[music] and remains visible.
And so also the difference between these
uh brushstrokes. [music]
So very smooth glazing areas, but also
the very upstanding, very
three-dimensional highlights.
>> That that's a difference that I always
notice with Rubens.
The surfaces look very kind of liquid
almost, as if they haven't quite
solidified. There's that brilliant uh
sort of like skating feeling across the
plains.
>> Uh absolutely. Uh Rubens really loved to
paint on a smooth surface. [snorts]
Um
also on panel you could paint uh
very differently.
So his painting uh on panel became more,
let's say,
um atmospheric.
>> Now let's talk about this wood. Uh where
did it come from? I mean I think I I
read somewhere that a lot of it came
from from my country, from Poland.
>> Well, it comes exactly from Poland and
the Baltic region. Uh it was, let's say,
shipped towards um Antwerp. Um and then
when it arrived, it was, of course,
uh
>> [music]
>> cut into planks and then uh panels were
made. And these panels had standard
shapes. They had standard formats.
>> When you look at Rubens though, quite
often you see the lines, don't you? You
can still see the lines where the panels
were. So it wasn't made from one panel,
it was made from separate pieces.
>> That has to do with the fact that
Rubens, when he developed his ideas, was
one of the first uh painters that uh
didn't take the format for granted. So,
while he's thinking about his
composition, he often enlarges it.
And a good example for us is is the
Madonna with a Parrot, which started as
a smaller Madonna picture and then
completely overworked or completely
over-painted, and so it became this very
baroque, very Italianate
uh large piece.
>> Maybe we can have a closer look as well.
>> So, the painting was started by Rubens
in 1614.
Uh and the painting was in fact uh was a
standing format from approximately here
to there.
And high as such.
>> So, just a a Madonna and Child.
>> and Child without a parrot with it, St.
Joseph, uh
so only the Madonna.
Then
the painting was still in his studio. He
didn't sell it, apparently. And then in
1630, he turned it into uh something
which is far grander, a far more
monumental. So, more an Italianate
Venetian
uh painting.
>> It's so interesting though. So, can I
ask though, what why would he bother
doing that? I mean, you've got a picture
here which um you know, by Ruben's
standard is quite modest. Uh why why
didn't he just start from scratch? Why
why would he begin to enlarge it like
this?
>> Never waste something that exists and
transform it into your idiom of the
moment. I think he wanted to get rid of
uh an older Madonna he he couldn't sell
or he didn't sell. And
uh
>> And makes it a much more glorious
painting.
>> Absolutely.
>> I'll tell you what I really like here.
This red.
>> Absolutely.
>> Well, Ruben's is red.
>> It's like a lipstick on a on a woman's
lips.
>> That's his color. That's his color.
His balance of colors is always turning
to the reds.
The reds are all his.
One of the big criticisms that's always
leveled at Rubens is that he turned out
too many pictures.
His studio was the biggest and busiest
in Europe. So, there are a lot of
Rubens's out there. Too many for one man
to have painted.
So, the worry is his assistants did it
all for him.
It's true. He was amazingly prolific.
And to achieve all that Rubens achieved
did require the assistance of a busy
[music] studio.
But, why is that so terrible?
We don't expect an architect to lay all
his own bricks
or a composer to play all the
instruments.
So, why in art are we so reluctant to
[music] admire
a collaborative effort?
Now, this little picture is by Rubens
and by Jan Breughel.
So's this one.
And this one.
They're so petite.
Look, five exciting little pictures
packed, rammed
with so much stuff.
They're actually allegories of the
senses. Five of them.
Each picture a different sense.
This one here with all the flowers,
that's the sense of smell.
The one with the telescope in it and all
the magnifying gizmos,
that's sight.
And this one, my favorite, with Venus
playing a lute and Cupid singing,
that's hearing.
The actual music that Venus and Cupid
are playing in the picture and that
you're listening to now
is a madrigal by the 16th century
English composer Peter Philips.
And all those notes on the table,
those are the actual notes.
The musical instruments are perfectly
identifiable, too.
The birds are all birds that are famous
for talking.
The cause,
a cockatoo,
and under the keyboard, a cheeky toucan.
To work out all the symbolism packed
into these five paintings would take
several hours.
So, my advice to you is to come back
here to the Prado one day and to spend
the whole day in front of Brueghel and
Rubens. You'll really enjoy it.
But why is Rubens working with Brueghel?
Who did what in these exciting
allegories?
And why?
Brueghel was renowned as a still life
painter and he specialized in these busy
allegories.
He was actually taught to paint
miniatures by his grandmother. And some
of the detail in this picture is so fine
that he had to paint it with a brush
that only had one hair.
So, most of what you see here was
painted by Brueghel
who'd lay out the picture and pack it
with details.
But, he'd leave empty spaces for Venus
and Cupid.
And the picture was then taken round the
corner to Rubens' studio.
And Rubens would put in the figures.
What an extraordinary way to make
pictures. The question is,
why bother?
It certainly wasn't because Brueghel
couldn't do the figures himself.
In his own art, like this bustling
country road in Brabant,
Brueghel was perfectly capable of doing
all sorts of figures.
Brueghel didn't collaborate with Rubens
because he couldn't do figures.
Brueghel collaborated with Rubens, his
friend and neighbor, because their joint
achievement was more valuable than an
individual achievement.
Brueghel pulled Rubens in a different
direction.
Their shared accomplishment was
something more than a solo
accomplishment.
And is collaboration
really such a bad thing when it gives us
art as good as this?
Ah, not Blake. You must agree that
Rubens was a fool and yet you make him
master of your school.
Rubens, a fool.
He just doesn't get it, does he?
Just doesn't get it.
Rubens was anything but a fool.
If he'd never been a painter, he'd still
have been an important figure in another
crucial field of European history.
Politics.
Rubens was the most politically active
and powerful artist there's ever been.
He was the Henry Kissinger of his times.
To have achieved what he did in politics
while keeping down his day job as
Europe's greatest painter was
remarkable.
To give you a sense of the twisted
political realities of Rubens's world,
here's his head of Medusa, painted in
1617.
See Medusa's hair, how knotted and slimy
and slippery it is?
Well, the politics of Rubens's world
were like that.
>> [music]
>> To understand what was going on in
Rubens's day between Spain, France,
England,
the Spanish Netherlands, and the
breakaway Dutch provinces, you don't
just need a degree in history, you need
to be pretty good at geometry, too, and
biology. It's very complicated.
Isabella, the ruler of the Spanish
Netherlands,
was married to her cousin Albert. So,
they were both Habsburgs and together
they ruled the Spanish Netherlands.
And this Habsburg connection is crucial.
Because Isabella was also the daughter
of Philip II, the Habsburg king of
Spain, who you may remember was king of
England, too, when he briefly married
Queen Mary, the daughter of Henry VIII.
Now, Philip's dream
was to restore Catholicism to England.
That's why he sent over the Spanish
Armada to conquer England.
However, back in the Spanish
Netherlands,
Philip's daughter, Isabella, didn't want
war with England. She wanted peace.
Because Isabella's dream was to restore
a united Netherlands. And that's also
what Rubens wanted.
In 1621,
Albert, Isabella's husband and cousin,
died. And that left Isabella
as the sole ruler of the Spanish
Netherlands. And so heartbroken was she
by Albert's death that she retired from
courtly life
and became
a nun,
a poor Clare, as they were called.
From now on,
>> [music]
>> she ran the country from a monastery
with the help of her closest political
advisor,
her court painter,
Rubens.
>> [snorts]
[bell]
>> As the greatest artist in Europe, Rubens
was welcomed at every court.
Everyone wanted to be painted by him.
And while he was painting them, well,
there was lots of time, wasn't there, to
discuss a bit of politics,
share some confidences,
make a couple of suggestions.
Back at the Eighty Years War,
Isabella helping to achieve peace,
needed Spain to ally herself with her
historic enemy, England.
So, she sent her best diplomat,
Rubens,
to Spain, where his task was to persuade
the new Spanish king,
Philip the Fourth,
who was Isabella's nephew,
to enter into a new alliance
with Charles the First and England.
And that's why in 1629,
having smooth-talked Philip the Fourth
round to Isabella's way of thinking,
Rubens arrived in London and set about
charming Charles the First as well.
>> [music]
>> This was actually painted by Rubens's
greatest pupil, Van Dyck.
It still hangs in Buckingham Palace
today.
How do you get a king to eat out of your
hand?
You put him on a big horse and give him
the bearing of a mighty warrior.
It's what's called the Rubens way.
>> And it didn't stop there.
To ingratiate himself further with
Charles the first, Rubens offered to
paint the ceiling of this famous
building here, Inigo Jones's Banqueting
House in Whitehall.
>> It's the only great painted ceiling by
Rubens that's still in situ, in the
place for which it was painted.
All this art, all this effort and time
and invention
lavished on England in the pursuit of
peace.
>> And do you know what?
It worked.
All this cunning artistic diplomacy by
Rubens worked.
And to thank Rubens for his diplomatic
services, Charles knighted him and also
gave him a diamond-studded
hatband for his hat.
>> For Rubens though, enough was enough.
He was a painter, not a diplomat.
Having successfully engineered a peace
between Britain and Spain,
the Henry Kissinger of the Baroque
returned to Antwerp and gave up politics
forever.
From now on, Rubens's attention was
claimed fully by his day job.
And by the other great love of his life,
women.
>> [bell]
>> Isabella Brant had died of the plague in
1626,
and a lonely Rubens needed to find a new
wife.
The one he found, Helene Fourment,
would become one of the most painted
women in art.
>> Helene Fourment was 16 when she married
Rubens, and he was 53.
Now, in those days, it was less of an
issue, but it was still
unexpected.
>> Rubens' friends thought he'd choose a
countess, or maybe a duchess.
That's how high he'd climbed up the
social ladder.
Instead, he chose the daughter of a
tapestry salesman.
Homely,
unpretentious,
and beautiful
in a full-bodied Flemish way.
>> Rubens was always a very sensual
painter, very physical, unusually
physical.
And his art often makes very clear how
much he enjoyed
the pleasurable side of marriage.
>> Helene Fourment begins to appear and
reappear in his pictures
with remarkable frequency.
Sometimes, she's a country girl.
Sometimes, a goddess.
Sometimes, she's all over the place
and pops up throughout the picture.
And sometimes
she's entirely undisguised.
Rubens' wife, mother of his children,
the woman he loves.
This is the most notorious of his
depictions of her, Helene Fourment in a
fur coat. It's notorious because
well,
you can see why, can't you?
It's not every day that a great painter
shows us his wife
like this.
She's just had a bath.
And as she steps towards us,
she's grabbed a handful of fur and
wrapped it round herself to cover
herself up.
But the fur's not doing very well, is
it?
There's more of Helene Fourment poking
out
than poking in.
It's actually another clever bit of
role-playing. She's meant to be Venus,
the goddess of love, the most famous
woman ever to step out of the sea naked
and wet.
And it's Venus in a particular guise,
what they call Venus Pudica, the shy
Venus.
It's the same Venus that Botticelli
painted in his most famous picture,
coming out of the sea, covering herself
up so shyly.
But look how vividly Rubens updates her
shyness.
How real he makes it.
There's an awkwardness to her, isn't
there? As there would be if you had to
stand about like that.
But, the fur coat, that's a brilliant
touch, which plucks her out of the
clouds and brings her right back down to
earth in Antwerp in the 1630s.
I love her dimply knees.
And that soft tummy of hers.
That's not the tummy of a goddess.
That's the tummy of [music] a real
woman.
Rubens has cast his wife as the Venus of
Antwerp.
But, he's also worshipping her evident
humanity.
A happy man in a happy marriage is
making clear in his art how he feels
about the woman he loves.
Isn't that marvelous?
I think we need a summary to count up
all the things that Rubens achieved.
One.
He painted some of the most exciting and
dramatic religious art of the Baroque
era.
Two. He painted some very entertaining
mythologies and broke world records for
filling his pictures with cheeky cherubs
and fleshy nudes.
Three. He was a great portraitist.
His portraits are so vivid and
compelling.
Particularly his portraits of his wives.
How touching they are.
Four. Size-wise, his scale is
unchallenged.
No one painted art as big and as
ambitious as Rubens' is
Which takes me straight to number five.
Which is how madly inventive he was.
Everywhere you look in Rubens, something
remarkable is going on.
Six. Technically, he was as good as any
painter has ever been.
A wizard of the paintbrush who made the
paint sing and the colors dance.
>> [snorts]
>> Seven. He collaborated with some of the
best artists of his time.
And the results of this exciting
pictorial democracy are glorious.
Eight. And this is something I haven't
even had time to deal with yet. But
believe it or not, Rubens designed
wonderful tapestries.
And at the convent of the Poor Clares in
Madrid, you get a really good sense of
how big and spectacular his tapestries
were.
Nine. And I haven't been able to fit
this in either. He was an architect. And
the Church of the Jesuits in Antwerp,
with that superb facade,
that was Rubens' handywork, too.
So here's a man who could achieve all
that. Surely, he couldn't do any more.
Well, actually, he could. Because Rubens
was also a great landscape painter. And
that is number 10.
When Rubens married Hélène Fourment,
they moved out here to the Château de
Steen,
the great country house they shared so
happily.
Where Rubens' is art put on its wellies
and began filling its lungs with fresh
country air.
This part of Flanders, around the
Chateau de Steen, is called Brabant, and
this was his inspiration.
Oh, look, some goldfinches.
Oh, look, a kingfisher.
In his revolutionary landscapes,
Rubens' brush explores the Brabant
countryside like a happy dog.
No one had painted landscapes as fresh
and airy as these before.
And look how big they are.
And how far away the horizon seems
in these endless panoramas.
He did night scenes, too. There's a
particularly beautiful one at the
Courtauld Galleries in London.
The evening sky twinkling with dreamy
stars, and such a gorgeous atmosphere of
romance.
Rubens at his soppiest, melting the
hardest heart.
But he could do storms, too.
They're some of the fiercest in art.
You wouldn't want to be out in a Rubens
storm.
Rubens' views from his window celebrate
nature's many moods.
Having reinvented everything else,
Rubens at his final contribution,
reinvents the landscape, too.
That's the kind of man we're dealing
with here.
>> [music]